Preliminary Inventory to the A. Daniel O'Neal Papers, 1973-1979
Hoover Institution Archives
A. Daniel O'Neal Papers,
1973-1979
88003
O'Neal, A. Daniel (Arthur Daniel), 1936-
68 manuscript boxes (28.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, correspondence, reports, memoranda, legal documents, notes, and printed matter, relating to federal regulation of interstate commerce, and especially to regulation of railways and motor carriers.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United States. Interstate Commerce Commission; United States--Commerce; Transportation--United States; Railroads--United States; Transportation, Automotive--United States; Interstate commerce; United States--Politics and government
Biographical Note
1936 May 15 Born, Bremerton, Washington
1965-1967 Staff Counsel, Senate Commerce Committee
1967-1969 Legal Assistant, Office of Senator Warren Magnuson
1969-1971 Surface Transportation Counsel, Senate Commerce Committee
1971-1973 Transportation Counsel, Senate Commerce Committee
1973-1977 Commissioner, Interstate Commerce Commission
1977-1979 Chairman, Interstate Commerce Commission
1977-1979 Board of Directors, U.S. Railway Association
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE. (Box 1)
  Biographical sketch and photographs, ca. 1977-1979.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1973-1979. (Boxes 2-16)
  Speech transcripts, interviews, correspondence, printed material, agenda, newsletters, outlines and notes relating primarily to the Interstate Commerce Commission and transportation issues. Arranged chronologically.
- INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION, PERSONAL OFFICE FILES, 1973-1979. (Boxes 17-22)
  Travel forms, appointment calendars, conference materials, miscellany, correspondence, invitations, clippings, press releases, and tally sheets (commission voting records). Arranged alphabetically by form.
- INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION, GENERAL OFFICE FILES, 1969-1982. (Boxes 23-26)
  Memoranda, notes, correspondence, press releases, printed material, biographies, legislation, reports, hearing transcripts, and meeting materials. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION DECISIONS, 1970-1979. (Boxes 27-54)
  Memoranda, correspondence, legal documents, notes, printed material, charts, budgets, conference materials, and reports. Arranged alphabetically by decision designation code.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1972-1980. (Boxes 55-63)
  Reports, printed material, correspondence, notes, conference materials, memoranda, speeches, legal documents, charts, press releases, regulations, maps and meeting notes. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE.
  - Biographical sketch and photographs, ca. 1977-1979 (Box 1.)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1973-1979
  - General. Speeches and statements, 1977-1979 (Box 64-68)
  - 1973 May-1974 Jan. (Box 2.)
  - 1974 Feb.-June (Box 3.)
  - 1974 June-1975 Feb. (Box 4.)
  - 1975 March-June (Box 5.)
  - 1975 June-Nov. (Box 6.)
  - 1975 Nov.-1976 May (Box 7.)
  - 1976 June-Oct. (Box 8.)
  - 1976 Nov.-1977 March (Box 9.)
  - 1977 March-May (Box 10.)
  - 1977 June-Oct. (Box 11.)
  - 1977 Oct.-1978 Jan. (Box 12.)
  - 1978 Feb.-Oct. (Box 13.)
  - 1978 Oct.-1979 March (Box 14.)
  - 1979 April-Sept. (Box 15.)
  - 1979 Sept.-Nov. (Box 16.)
- INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION, PERSONAL OFFICE FILES, 1973-1979
  - General. Travel forms, appointment calendars, conference material, and other miscellany, 1973-1979 (Box 17.)
  - Chronological files. Primarily correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 18.)
  - Correspondence. Includes letters of congratulations and thanks, 1976-1977
  - Invitations (Box 19.)
    - General, 1974-1979
    - Speaking engagements, 1973-1979 (Box 20.)
  - Press materials. Press releases and clippings, 1979 (Box 21.)
  - Tally sheets. Commission voting records, 1974-1979 (Box 22.)
- INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION, GENERAL OFFICE FILES, 1969-1982
  - General
    - General. Memoranda and notes ("unfinished business"), 1978 (Box 23., Folder 1)
    - Meetings. Conference memoranda, transcripts and notes, 1977 (Folder 2-4)
  - Commission organization and administration. Printed material, letters, press release, notes, memoranda and biographies, 1969-1979 (Folder 5-16)
  - Communications. Memoranda, correspondence, notes and printed material, 1977-1982 (Folder 17-19)
  - General Counsel. Correspondence and memoranda, 1979 (Box 24., Folder 1-2)
  - Intragovernmental coordination
    - General
      - Presidential meetings. Notes, summary, and letter, 1978 (Folder 3)
      - Regulatory chairmen meetings. Memoranda, 1978 (Folder 4)
    - Federal Maritime Commission. Memoranda, correspondence, notes, and legal documents, 1977-1979 (Folder 5)
    - Transportation Department. Memoranda, correspondence and notes, 1977 (Folder 6)
    - U.S. Congress. Correspondence, notes and memoranda, printed copies of legislation, reports and hearings, 1970-1979 (Folder 7-13)
    - U.S. Congress (Box 25., Folder 1)
  - Investigations and enforcement. Memorandum and charts, 1977 (Folder 2)
  - Personnel. Printed material, lists, photographs, memoranda, notes and biographies, 1972-1979 (Folder 3-9)
  - Policy. Memoranda, reports, charts, printed material, meeting minutes, 1975-1979 (Folder 10-15)
  - Policy (Box 26., Folder 1-8)
- INTERSTATE COMMERCE COMMISSION DECISIONS, 1970-1979
  - General
    - General. Primarily letters and memoranda relating to the administrative law process and judicial review; includes the personal dockets of Commissioner O'Neal, as well as miscellaneous cases, 1974-1979 (Box 27.)
    - Dissents by Commissioner O'Neal. Primarily legal memoranda and printed copies of decisions
      - 1973-1975 (Box 28.)
      - 1976-1979 (Box 29.)
  - Ex parte decisions. SEE ALSO: Motor carriers (Box 30.)
    - "Rail Appellate Procedures," (No. 55), 1978-1979
    - "Regulations for Rates and Charges," (No. 73/MC-1), 1973-1977
    - "International Joint Rates and Through Rates," (No. 261), 1973-1975 (Box 31.)
    - International Joint Rates and Through Rates," (No. 261) (Box 32.)
    - "Investigation of Railroad Freight Service," (No. 270), 1978-1979
    - "Abandonment Procedures for Bankrupt Railroads," (No. 274), 1979
    - "Remittance of Demurrage Charges by Common Carriers of Property by Rail," (No. 289), 1975-1977
    - "Remittance of Demurrage Charges by Common Carriers of Property by Rail," (No. 289) (Box 33.)
    - "Nationwide Increase of 10% in Freight Rates and Charges," (No. 305), 1974-1978 (Box 34.)
    - "Nationwide Increase of 10% in Freight Rates and Charges," (No. 305) (Box 35.)
    - "Nationwide Increase of 10% in Freight Rates and Charges," (No. 305) (Box 36.)
    - "Nationwide Increase of 10% in Freight Rates and Charges," (No. 305) (Box 37.)
    - "Valuation of Common Carrier Pipelines," (No. 308), 1972-1976
    - "Valuation of Common Carrier Pipelines," (No. 308) (Box 38.)
    - "Increased Freight Rates and Charges--Labor Costs-- 1975," (No. 313), 1975 (Box 39.)
    - "Investigation of Freight Rates for Transportation of Recyclable and Recycled Materials," (No. 319), 1976-1979
    - "Investigation of Freight Rates for Transportation of Recyclable and Recycled Materials," (No. 319) (Box 40.)
    - "Investigation of Freight Rates for Transportation of Recyclable and Recycled Materials," (No. 319) (Box 41.)
    - "Special Proceedings for Making Findings of Market Dominance," (No. 320), 1976-1979
    - "Special Proceedings for Making Findings of Market Dominance," (No. 320) (Box 42.)
    - "Substituted Service--Water-for Motor (Fishyback Service)--Alaskan Trade," (No. 325), 1976-1979
    - "Regulations Governing the Transfer of General Increases from Master Tariffs into the Individual Tariffs of Railroad or Ratemaking Organizations," (No. 326), 1978 (Box 43.)
    - "Consideration of the Revenue Adequacy Factor in Individual Rate Proceedings," (No. 338), 1978
    - "Change of Policy--Railroad Contract Rates," (No. 358), 1979
    - "Railroad-Freight Forwarder Contract Rates," (No. 364), 1979
    - "Increased Freight Rates and Charges, Nationwide," (No. 368), 1979
    - "Impact of Commission Decisions on Small Businesses," (No. 373), 1979
  - Financial dockets (Box 44.)
    - "Great Northern Pacific & Burlington Lines, Inc.--Merger," (FD 21478), 1975-1979
    - "Amoskeag Company--Control--Maine Central Railroad Company," (FD 27620), 1975-1977
    - "Amoskeag Company--Control--Maine Central Railroad Company," (FD 27620), 1975-1977 (Box 45.)
    - "Burlington Northern, Inc.--Control and Merger--St. Louis-San Francisco Railway Company," (FD 28583), 1979
    - "CSX Corporation--Control--Chessie System, Inc., and Seaboard Coast Line Industries, Inc.," (FD 28905), 1979
    - "CSX Corporation--Control--Chessie System, Inc., and Seaboard Coast Line Industries, Inc.," (FD 28905) (Box 46.)
    - "Auto-Train Corporation," (FD 29062), 1972-1979 (Box 47.)
    - "Milwaukee Railroad Restructuring Act," (FD 29171), 1979
    - "Investigation into the Management, Business Inter-relationship and Transactions of the Kansas City Southern Railway Company and Louisiana and Arkansas Railway Company," (FD 35288), 1970-1973
    - "Investigation into the Management, Business Inter-relationship and Transactions of the Kansas City Southern Railway Company and Louisiana and Arkansas Railway Company," (FD 35288), 1970-1973 (Box 48.)
    - "Montana Interstate Rail Freight Rates and Charges," (FD 36053), 1975-1977
    - "Revision of Rules on Classification of Carriers," (FD 36137), 1975 (Box 49.)
    - "Corporate Disclosure Regulations," (FD 36141), 1975-1977
    - "San Antonio, Texas Acting by and through its City Public Service Board," (36180), 1977-1979 (Box 50.)
    - "Increased Rates on Coal, L&N Railroad," (37063), 1979
  - Investigation and suspension
    - "Cancellation of Joint Rates on Potash, Ann Arbor," (IS 9207), 1979
  - Motor carriers
    - General. Policy materials
    - "General Increase, Southern Motor Carriers Rate Conference," (IS M-29772), 1978-1979 (Box 51.)
    - "Commercial Zones and Terminal Areas," (Ex parte No. MC-37), 1975-1977 (Box 52.)
    - "Transportation of Mobile Homes," (Ex parte No. MC-108), 1977-1979 (Box 53.)
    - "Policy Statement on Motor Carrier Regulation," (Ex parte No. MC-121)
    - "Revenue Need Standards in Motor Carrier General Proceedings," (Ex parte No. MC-128), 1979
    - "Master Certificates and Permits--Petition to Establish Orderly Procedures for Service and Replies to Comments of Interested Parties," (Ex parte No. 135), 1979
    - "Municipal Tank Lines, Limited, Extension--Common Carrier Application," (MC-138762), 1978-1979 (Box 54.)
    - "Bud's Moving and Storage, Inc., Petition for Declaratory Order," (MC-C-8687), 1976-1977
- SUBJECT FILE, 1972-1980
  - Abandonment alternatives. Memoranda and notes, 1979 (Box 55., Folder 1)
  - Alaskan pipeline system. Conference materials, reports, printed material, letters, notes, photographs, and miscellany, 1975-1979 (Folder 2-6)
  - American Bar Association. Notebook of materials relating to a conference entitled "Oversight and Review of Agency Decisionmaking," 1976 March (Folder 7)
  - AMTRAK. ICC reports to the president, 1978-1979 (Box 56., Folder 1)
  - Ann Arbor Railroad. Memoranda, 1979 (Folder 2)
  - Bus industry. Materials relating to a report by a bus industry study group, 1979 (Folder 3-4)
  - Coal slurry pipelines. Notes, statement, reports, printed materials, letters, 1972-1975 (Folder 5)
  - Compliance enforcement. Work group report, 1979 (Folder 6)
  - CONFAC. Printed material and a speech, 1975 (Folder 7)
  - Conglomerates. Primarily printed articles, and memorandum, 1969-1975 (Folder 8)
  - Conrail. Memoranda, notes, and a report entitled "Alternatives for Conrail" with background materials, 1979 (Folder 9-10)
  - Delaware and Hudson Railroad. Memoranda, notes, reports, 1977-1978 (Box 57., Folder 1)
  - Designated operators. Memoranda and report, 1976 (Folder 2)
  - Eastern Freightways/Associated Transport. Notes, press release, correspondence, memoranda, printed materials, legal materials, investigation reports, printed materials, 1975-1976 (Folder 3-5)
  - Empty backhaul. Memoranda, letter, printed material and report, 1975-1976 (Folder 6)
  - Energy. Memoranda, printed material, reports, correspondence, charts, press releases, meeting notes, legal documents (E.P. 311), and miscellany, 1973-1979 (Box 58., Folder 1-3)
  - Freight cars. Lists, and notes; relates to supply and per diem rates, 1975 (Folder 4)
  - Grand Trunk Western Railroad/Detroit, Toledo merger. Maps, charts, memoranda, notes, miscellany, 1979 (Folder 5-6)
  - Household Goods Transportation Act of 1979. Statements and press release, 1979 (Folder 7)
  - Integrated oil operations. Printed material, memorandum and draft statement, 1973-1974 (Folder 8)
  - Intercorporate hauling regulation. Report with cover memorandum, 1979 (Folder 9)
  - Intermodal-TOFC/COFC conference. Memorandum, notes, and regulations, 1979 (Folder 10)
  - Labor protection agreements. Report, 1972 (Folder 11)
  - Legislation. Memoranda, and printed material, 1979 (Folder 12)
  - Mergers. Press release, maps, and printed material relating to railway mergers, 1963-1969 (Box 59., Folder 1)
  - Middle distillates. Statement, 1979 (Folder 2)
  - Milwaukee Railroad. Memoranda and reports of a conference relating to a rate increase, 1978 (Folder 3)
  - Motor carriers. Reports, survey, memoranda, printed material, press release, draft policy statement, notes, correspondence with the White House and others, conference materials, 1977-1978 (Folder 4-8)
  - Motor carriers. Proposals of the Motor Carrier Task Force, conference materials, memoranda, notes, printed material, list, speech transcript, meeting notes and agenda, 1975-1979 (Box 60., Folder 1-3)
  - Pipeline. Report, memoranda, notes and decision, 1975-1976 (Folder 4)
  - Platform study. Notes and memorandum, 1979 (Folder 5)
  - Productivity. Pamphlet, statements and miscellany relating to railroads, 1974 (Folder 6)
  - Railroads
    - General. Notes, charts, printed material, reports and memoranda relating to regulation, nationalization, rates, 1971-1980 (Folder 7-10)
    - Railroad Revitalization and Regulatory Reform Act of 1976. Reports and memoranda, 1976-1979 (Box 61., Folder 1-4)
  - REA Express. Memorandum, 1979 (Folder 5)
  - Regulatory oversight. Letter, memorandum, speech transcript and printed material, 1974-1975 (Folder 6)
  - Release rates. Memorandum, 1976 (Folder 7)
  - Rock Island Railroad. Notes, memoranda, printed material, letters, reports, hearing summaries, charts; relates primarily to a proposed merger, 1974-1979 (Folder 8-9)
  - Rock Island Railway. Reports, memoranda and notes, 1973-1975 (Box 62., Folder 1-3)
  - Teamsters Union. Letter to the President, 1979 (Folder 4)
  - Transportation Acts. Reports, memoranda, correspondence, printed material, 1970-1974 (Box 63., Folder 1-3)
  - Voting trust agreement. Memoranda, notes, letters, report, and printed material, 1975-1978 (Folder 4-5)
  - Weight bumping. Memoranda and correspondence primarily relating to a "60 Minutes" broadcast, 1978-197 (Folder 6-7)